That warning is coming from your heart
and you can detect it if you know how.
We'll get into it along with the science
behind it. This warning sign is called
heart rate variability or HRV. It's
simply the variation in time between
heartbeats. Your heart doesn't beat
exactly every x amount of milliseconds.
It varies. Hence the variability
component. Unfortunately, it's not
something that we can detect by simply,
you know, taking our pulse. But
fortunately, it does tell us an
indication of our health, our risk of
death, as we'll get into. The more
adaptable your heart rate variability,
the better one's health generally. Why
is that? It speaks to a concept of
veagal tone. This was a fascinating
concept that I learned about during my
exercise physiology masters program. In
fact, I'll explain why in a minute. But
veagal tone is an incredibly important
bundle of neurons that extend from your
brain stem to your heart. There it
controls your heart rhythm by branching
and innervating or connecting at two
major sites at the heart. The SA node or
sinoatrial node and the AV node or
atrial ventricular node. These regions
of your heart control your heart rhythm
and the vagus nerve actually slows your
heart down. So more veagal tone or
input, the slower your heart rate. Okay,
but why does any of that actually
matter? Well, multiple things influence
your vag nerve and its function. Your
blood pressure can influence the vagus
nerve through sensors in your heart and
the corroted artery called bar
receptors. Uh cortisol from stress can
suppress the veagal tone as well. And in
the reverse direction, chronic bodily
inflammation is a sign of reduced veagal
tone as the vagus nerve can also reduce
inflammation. There's plenty of other
ways of creating these connections. The
point being it isn't as simple as nerve
connect heart nerve good. There's a lot
of physiological interconnectedness
that translates into something that we
can pick up on by the heart rate
variability measure. If your physiology
is disregulated, unhealthy,
pathological, even it uh gets picked up
by this metric heart, heart rate
variability. By the way, uh one of the
fascinating things I learned about uh
related to this vag nerve is that uh if
you were to remove your heart from your
body, effectively separating it from the
vag nerve, your heart rate would
increase up to 100 beats per minute. So,
in the Indiana Jones movie, The Temple
of Doom, the heart taken out of that one
poor fellow probably should have been
beating faster. Now, if only they'd
consulted me for accuracy, something
that they were clearly concerned with.
Not to mention that I didn't exist. But
let's put all those minor inconveniences
aside. Okay, we know how physiologically
speaking, heart rate variability ties
into telling us about veagal tone and
several indices of health, but does that
actually bear out in the studies or am I
just talking out of my rear end?
Fortunately, there are recent analyses
on this very topic like this one and
this one. In this analysis, researchers
quantified the risk of having a high
heart rate variability or HRV versus low
HRV on all-c causeed mortality and
cardiovascular mortality. This was
assessed in about 3,000 people already
diagnosed with cardiovascular disease.
Then they tracked these people over 1 to
nine years to determine who died over
that time and if more deaths occurred in
relation to low or high HRV. If we pop
open that data for all cause mortality,
we see the included studies in the
analysis along with the different ways
that HRV was measured on the far left.
The poolled HR or hazard ratio indicates
the risk of an event in the low HRV
groups versus the higher HRV groups. If
the numbers are greater than one, that's
increased risk. That's also represented
in the middle with the dots and the
lines from the dots. These correspond to
the numbers that we just saw for the
hazard ratio. What you need to know is
if they move to the right of the
vertical line there, there indicates
increased risk. So across all these
measurement types along with all these
studies, the vast majority of the
studies fall to the right or at least on
the line indicating a trend for
increased mortality risk with lower HRV.
But like I briefly mentioned, this is in
people with cardiovascular disease. So,
is this still true in people who are not
diagnosed with some pre-existing
cardiovascular problem? For that, we can
lean on this analysis that included a
much larger 38,000 participants, of
which a majority were classified as
healthy, although not all. And these
researchers did something pretty
similar, comparing the risk with low
versus high HRV. So, are these results
consistent? Well, let's take a look.
Now, normally I'd walk you through this,
but this is such a mess and so difficult
to read that I think uh we'll just
switch this out for a more
comprehensive, slightly easier to read
graph. Here, we follow the same rules as
the first graph that we looked at. The
more it moves to the right, the greater
the mortality risk from lower HRV.
Again, almost all the sub analyses
indicate either an increased risk or no
relationship. In totality, it might
indicate an increased risk with lower
HRV. However, okay, so is that it? We
just move on to what to look for for
HRV? No. There's several things to say
about these analyses. First, these
analyses are the only recent ones that I
could find looking at all cause
mortality, but that doesn't make them
particularly good. For example, the
first analysis included 28 studies,
which seems like a lot, but with only
3,000 or so participants included, this
is a small analysis. My more major gripe
with these analyses is the poor
adjustments, as in uh poorly controlling
for outside influencing factors that
could explain these results. In fact, of
the 28 studies included in the analysis,
23 adjusted for age, 14 adjusted for
sex, 11 adjusted for diabetes. I mean,
talk about all over the place.
Generally, you'd want to have some sort
of consistency and controls for
confounders across all the included
studies because otherwise, you'll see a
significant heterogeneity in the
results. And what do you know? If we
look at the heterogeneity tests here, we
see a lot. In addition, the researchers
included a bunch of different ways of
measuring HRV, but each type of
measurement has a different
sensitivities and may even evaluate HRV
differently, speaking to different
information that we can glean from HRV.
So, lumping them all together just
contributes to that heterogeneity.
Overall, either this analysis just
shouldn't have been performed because
they did several things poorly in my
mind or they should have just limited it
to uh the data that could be more
uniform and restrict their question more
so as not to distill it with
inapplicable data. Whatever does that
then mean that all of this has been
nonsense then? Well, I don't think so.
We can still say there's a relationship
between HRV and mortality, although it
isn't as you know clean as I'd like it
to be, which means we definitely need
more targeted studies. Still, clearly
there's a signal when adjusting for some
major confounding factors, even if not
all. Plus, we're not actually saying
that HRV is contributing to mortality,
just that it's a signal for it, which it
seems to be. Okay, that mentioned, we've
been discussing low and high HRV and how
low HRV is indicative of mortality risk.
Well, we'll get into what to look for
when measuring your HRV. But if you're
interested in a step-by-step guide on
how to accurately measure your HRV along
with the most sensitive consumer grade
equipment, check out my Physionic
Insiders membership. It can be found
there. In addition, you'll also get
access to all my work along with other
guides, templates, exclusive videos,
written research reviews, live sessions
with me, and much more. The link is in
the description. Hope to see you there,
assuming your heart's up for it. Now,
what's a low HRV to avoid? Well, a few
things to say here. First, you'll need
some form of HRV reader, like a monitor,
a wearable with a sensor capable of
identifying HRV. An Apple Watch can do
it with limited capacity, for example.
Then, as you saw from the graphs,
there's a bunch of different ways of
assessing HRV. These are based on a time
domain or frequency domain measurement
styles. We can ignore the frequency
domain because it's not typically
measured by consumer wearables and can
be controversial. So, by the power of
logic, we're left with time domain
measurements. Even there there are
different types but the most common in
wearable devices are SDN or standard
deviation of all normal to normal
intervals really rolls off the tongue as
well as RMSSD a root mean square
successive differences between adjacent
NN intervals again they left the
hospital called that so let's respect
their choice and name anyway this is all
to explain that there are two methods
that we can used to assess HRV. Most
wearable watches like an Apple Watch or
other wearables like UA and others only
detect RMSSD, so we'll focus on that.
And they do the math for you, so you
don't need to strain your brain to high
school math trying to remember how
square roots work. The RMSSD, which is a
measure of veagal tone that we described
earlier, cutoff is 20 milliseconds. So
if you have an HRV measured by RMSSSD
used in Apple Watch or Aura Ring and
most other basic wearables and your HRV
is above 20 milliseconds, you are at
lower risk of mortality and your
physiology detected by HRV indicates
robustness and overall decent health.
Now, I'll discuss more on the specifics
of HRV and more pre precise measures
using SDNN in my guide included with the
Physionic Insiders, but I should caution
a few things here. One, the research was
rudimentarily
split between less than 20 milliseconds
and over 20 milliseconds. That doesn't
inform on what is normal and a 20
millisecond HRV is quite low. So the
general idea is that uh the higher one's
HRV, the better, assuming that there
isn't some underlying pathology screwing
up the reading. However, if your HRV is
closer to 20 milliseconds, it might be
an indication to consider looking at
your life habits and working on them,
nutrition, exercise, sleep, stress, and
so on. It's a very useful metric in that
regard. Two, consider taking an HRV
reading multiple times across multiple
days and averaging them. An overly
stressful or even relaxed day can give
you one reading and the next day can
offer you a completely different one.
Three, HRV isn't everything. It informs
us on certain physiological states. But
don't base something like cardiovascular
disease risk or cancer risk or something
to that effect based on a good HRV.
Disease can still be present itself in
spite of good readings. HRV is informing
on the general physiological state and
the relationship to general mortality.
So the main points here are that HRV or
heart rate variability has imperfect
evidence suggesting that it relates to
mortality risk. The lower one's HRV, the
greater their all-c causeed mortality
risk. You can assess your HRV using a
basic HRV reader like an Aura ring or an
Apple Watch or similar and hit a minimum
of above 20 milliseconds HRV to be in
reduced risk mortality based on this
analysis. Now, like a used car salesman,
how about an extended warranty on that
heart of yours? I can add another 50,000
mi on that heart by improving your HRV
through some of the most potent ways of
improving your general health. Just
sign, I mean, click right here.